Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we follow a
fascinating case study
on the reversal of
stage 3 cancer
with fasting.
After a cancer diagnosis,
the focus is understandably
on monitoring the spread
and resurgence of the cancer,
but patients often also want
to know what additional steps
they themselves can take
to support their body’s fight.
Previously, I addressed what to eat
after a cancer diagnosis.
What about eating
nothing at all?
Fasting is purported
to “ameliorate” cancers,
but to support such claims,
they cite studies like this
on castrated mice.
That’s because there are no
human studies of efficacy,
though there are
a few case reports.
For example: “Water-only fasting
and an exclusively plant foods diet
in the management
of... follicular lymphoma.”
Traditional chemotherapy has been
the mainstay of treatment
for follicular lymphoma.
But in the majority of patients,
the cancer surges back
within a few years, and the chemo
is associated with immediate
and enduring toxicities,
including secondary malignancies,
meaning new cancers caused
by the chemo drugs themselves,
raising the question
of whether chemotherapy
should be abandoned
for the disease.
So
anyway, a 42-year-old
woman presented
to her primary care provider
with a palpable mass
in her groin and was
immediately sent for a CT scan.
Surgical biopsy
confirmed the diagnosis
of a low-grade
follicular lymphoma.
They then found involvement
in the lymph nodes in her armpit,
which would make it stage 3,
meaning spread throughout the body.
Because it didn’t
appear to be aggressive,
she was just
advised to follow-up
every three months
to monitor its spread.
But she didn’t want
to just sit around.
So, she contacted the
TrueNorth Health Center in California
to explore medically
supervised, water-only fasting.
She had never smoked tobacco,
but she had consumed
the Standard American Diet;
so they started her
on a whole food plant
foods diet free
of added salt,
oil, and sugar.
Then, she did 21 days on water only,
before transitioning back to a diet
of minimally processed plant foods,
including fresh, raw fruits
and vegetables, steamed
and baked vegetables,
whole grains and legumes,
and about an ounce a day
of nuts and seeds.
Okay, so what happened?
On physical exam, her cancerous
lymph nodes seemed to be shrinking,
and indeed, on CT scan,
her enlarged nodes shrunk
up to 90 percent and no
longer seemed to be active.
Before and after.
What could it have been?
She did lose weight, about 20 pounds,
but follicular lymphoma does not appear
to be associated with obesity,
nor does BMI appear
to affect clinical outcomes.
It’s possible the plant-based
diet alone helped.
Follicular lymphoma is the
second most common type
of non-Hodgkin lymphoma, which itself
is the most common type
of blood cancer in adults.
Higher intakes of dietary fiber,
whole grains, and several fruits
and vegetables are
reported to reduce
the risk of non-Hodgkin lymphoma,
whereas animal-derived proteins
and fat in meat
and dairy may increase it.
A dietary pattern high
in meats, fats, and sweets
was associated with three times
the risk of follicular lymphoma,
or just the fat and meat
was associated
with up to a fivefold
higher risk. But why?
The thought that foods
of animal origin may increase
the risk of blood cancers
originated from the frequent finding
of an increased incidence among
people who are occupationally exposed
to animals and meats, like livestock
and poultry farmers, butchers,
and slaughterhouse workers.
It must be acknowledged that
animal foods are a potential source
of infection by
cancer-causing viruses.
But it may just be the animal protein.
Excessive consumption
of animal protein
may encourage malignant changes through
chronic persistent stimulation.
The thought is that
the continuous exposure
to these foreign proteins may
act like a chronic irritant.
The animal protein theory
is bolstered by the fact
that straight protein—
casein milk protein—
increases the number
of lymphomas in rats,
but that doesn’t mean
the same applies to people.
Maybe it’s the hormones
and antibiotics contained in meat
or just the saturated fat,
which may both impair
the immune system and promote
chronic inflammation,
which may play
a role in lymphoma?
Now, it appears to just
be animal fat consumption;
so, maybe it’s just something
building up in the animal fat?
There may be a link between
exposure to industrial pollutants
and non-Hodgkin lymphoma, and food—
especially meat, milk, and fish—
is the immediate
source of almost
all dioxins and PCBs in
the general population.
Dioxin-like pollutants
build up in animal fat,
which can then be passed
along to consumers.
Vegetarians may
only be exposed
to about 2 percent
of the dioxin dose
compared to the general population.
The highest single levels
in the U.S. have been found
in chicken, but thankfully
the contamination levels
are declining in all
meats across the board.
Furthermore, consumers may
further reduce exposures
to dioxin-like compounds by trimming
fat before and after cooking
and by thoroughly draining
fat from cooked meat.
What about buying organic meat?
When it comes to
carcinogenic contaminants,
the differences between organically
and conventionally produced meats
were surprisingly minimal,
exceeding the maximum limits
regardless of what
kind of meat we buy.
Strikingly, not only
does the consumption
of organically produced meat not
diminish the carcinogenic risk,
but for some meat,
it appeared even worse.
What can decrease your exposure
to fat-soluble pesticides is fiber.
And then, our good gut flora
can turn fiber into butyrate,
which is absorbed back
into our body from the colon
and acts as a tumor suppressor,
demonstrated in more than
one hundred published studies,
including protecting against lymphoma.
It also has potent
anti-inflammatory effects.
That may help explain why fruit
and vegetable consumption
has not only been associated
with decreased risk
of developing lymphoma, but also
been linked to improved survival.
Maybe it’s all the antioxidants
in plant foods,
which appear protective when it
comes to follicular lymphoma,
but not necessarily
when in supplement form.
Vitamin C intake
from foods, for example,
may be protective but not
from supplements.
So, maybe the reason the risk
of lymphomas and cancers
of the bone marrow tissues
are significantly lower
in vegetarians
and vegans is not just
because of what they’re avoiding,
but all the goodies that
they’re getting more of.
The phytochemicals and antioxidants
in fruits and vegetables
may inhibit tumor progression
via a variety of mechanisms
beyond just the potential
adverse effects of meat.
So, given the link between fruit
and vegetable intake
and lymphoma survival, maybe
a lymphoma diagnosis can be
an important ‘teachable’ moment
to improve diet in patients.
That certainly seemed
to be the case here.
At her six and nine-month follow-up,
she reported strict compliance
with her whole food plant-based
diet, and her lymph nodes
remained unpalpable.
Okay, but this
was published in 2015.
How’s she doing now?
We’ll find out next.
In 2015, a remarkable case report
was published in which a woman
with Stage 3 follicular lymphoma
underwent a medically supervised,
21-day water-only fast, after which
her enlarged lymph nodes
were substantially reduced in size.
The patient then remained
on a whole food, plant-based diet,
and at 6- and 9-month follow-up
visits she remained asymptomatic.
In 2018, her 3-year
follow-up was published.
Remarkably, she appeared
to remain cancer-free,
confirmed by CT and PET scans.
Her cancer appeared to have been
knocked down and out.
The initial regression has
persisted for the three years
with no additional intervention
other than the dietary change.
Could it have just
been a coincidence?
Sure, but the initial regression
directly coincided
with the timing of her water-only fast,
suggesting a causal relationship,
and there are biological mechanisms
by which fasting may potentiate
tumor regression, such as
decreasing levels of IGF-1.
The term "spontaneous regression"
of cancer is a misnomer.
I mean, obviously there was
something that caused the regression,
whether or not we know what it is.
Presumably the immune
system plays a role.
The fact that you can get
a marked increase in cancer rates
when you're immunosuppressed
suggests that cancers are popping up
all the time, but your immune system
is normally able to keep them at bay.
There was an example, for instance,
of a regression after a transfusion
of blood from a patient
who had previously sustained
a spontaneous regression.
Or cases of patients
who had been free of metastases
for 15 or 20 years, only to develop
rapidly fatal metastases after
some type of stress or shock
that apparently sharply
reduced their resistance.
For most cancers, spontaneous
regression is exceedingly rare,
but lymphoma is an exception.
Of 140 cases of nodular lymphoma --
which is what they used
to call follicular lymphoma --
there were 18 cases of at least partial
and 6 cases of complete regression.
So like 1 in 25 cases
just go away on their own.
So when you have
follicular lymphoma cases
in which tumors shrink
after any kind of treatment --
in this case after some
herbal supplement --
you always have to ask:
is this cause-and-effect
or just coincidence?
Elevated natural killing activity may
be one of the possible mechanisms
responsible for spontaneous
regression of malignant lymphoma.
Natural killer cells may be part
of our first line of defense
against cancer by
destroying tumor cells.
And if you compare
the natural killer cell activity
of those with malignant lymphoma
that spontaneously regressed
versus those whose cancer didn't,
or a control group,
the spontaneous regression group
does seem to be on the high end.
How can we increase
natural killer cell activity?
Exercise can do it,
unless, apparently,
you're eating a high-fat diet.
Those randomized to undergo
an exercise training program
on a high-fat diet actually
suffered a decline
in natural killer cell activity,
suggesting training on a high-fat diet
is detrimental to the immune system.
Eating lots of contaminated fatty fish
may also adversely
affect NK cell levels.
But put people on a low-fat diet,
and you can dramatically increase
natural killer cell activity within
a matter of months by about 50%,
suggesting that dietary fat might
increase the formation of cancer
by depressing the tumor surveillance
capacity of the immune system.
The bottom line in terms of fasting
is that, at present, long-term fasting
in cancer treatment is supported
only by some case reports,
so more research is
desperately needed.
Sadly, there is no
current clinical research
evaluating the effects of water-only
fasting and a whole food,
plant-based diet on follicular
lymphoma in humans.
Long-term fasting is
certainly not without risk.
In this case, a guy opted
to try a 60-day fast
instead of chemotherapy
for non-Hodgkin lymphoma,
ending up hospitalized
in a coma and respiratory failure
because of Wernicke encephalopathy,
a life-threatening
neurological emergency
caused by thiamine deficiency.
But starting on a healthier diet
seems like a win-win no-brainer.
Just putting people on a plant-based,
whole food, you know,
sugar-oil-salt-free diet,
with or without fasting,
is sometimes sufficient to induce
an intense healing response.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.